<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Here beginneth a] good lesson for yonge men</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1540</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05373</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15525</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121659</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856830</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856830</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22464</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05373)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22464)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 447:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Here beginneth a] good lesson for yonge men</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4+] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1540]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title and suggested publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A² +.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; a fragment of two leaves.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="fragment_of_poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:22464:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22464:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> good leſſon for yonge men.</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Trinitarian depiction of Christ with orb and right hand extended in blessing</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Myne owne dere chylde, I rede and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeyle the</l>
               <l>Whyle thou haſt youth,<note place="margin">
                     <q>Delicis iuue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis mee et igno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rantias meas: ne memineris. <bibl>Pſalme. 24.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note> &amp; ſtrength at thy wyll</l>
               <l>All ſynne and vyce, that thou refuſe and flee</l>
               <l>Thy precyous tyme, beware that thou do not ſpyll</l>
               <l>It renneth away, it ſtandeth neuer ſtyll</l>
               <l>Therfore beware, and fie from all outrage</l>
               <l>There dyeth mo yonge, than lyueth to great age.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:22464:2"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <q>
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <bibl>Pſalmus, 126</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e haſt ſpent</l>
               <l>for euery worde and dede, that thou haſt done</l>
               <l>Thou mayſt not ſcape, from thy iuſt Iugement</l>
               <l>Therfore do ſo, that thou nede not to repent</l>
               <l>That thyne enemyes, ſaye not to the chekmate</l>
               <l>when thou ſhalt paſſe, and mete them in the gate,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Let the drede of god, now be thy brydell</l>
               <l>And puruey for the tyme,<note place="margin">
                     <q>Initium ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entie timor do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini. <bibl>Pſa. 110</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note> that laſteth aye</l>
               <l>From vertuous occupacyon, be not ydell</l>
               <l>But get the ghoſtly rycheſſe, that thou may</l>
               <l>The fygure of this worlde, goeth faſt away</l>
               <l>He is ryche, that hath heuenly rycheſſe</l>
               <l>All worldly myrth, ſhall ende in heuyneſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ whyle thou arte yonge, be meke and ſeruyable</l>
               <l>Vnto thy ſouereygnes,<note place="margin">
                     <q>Intertoga pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem tuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciabit tibi maiores tuos et dicent tibi. <bibl>Deuter. 33.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note>
vſe thou gentyll ſpeche</l>
               <l>It is a thynge in youth, ryght co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendable</l>
               <l>To be more glad to lerne, than for to teche</l>
               <l>Tyll thou mayſt to more knowlege a reche</l>
               <l>He that wyll teache, or he any good can</l>
               <l>Ie wyll be longe, or he proue a wyſe man.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Fle from pryde, for that wyll haue a fall</l>
               <l>For god reſyſteth,<note place="margin">
                     <q>Iniquitatem ſi aſpexi in cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de meo: non ex audiet dominꝰ <bibl>Pſalmꝰ. 65.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note> proude men euermore</l>
               <l>Beware of enuy, it is better as gall</l>
               <l>Fle from wrath, or it wyll greue the ſore</l>
               <l>Kepe no malyce, within thyne herte in ſtore</l>
               <l>Theſe wycked rotes, be as a dethes darte</l>
               <l>My chylde ſet wyſely, kepynge to thy herte.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:22464:2"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Fle ryottous companye,<note place="margin">
                     <q>
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> chrietate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſecta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam et potan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad veſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peram vt vino eſtuetis, <bibl>Eſa. 5</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note> where ſo euer thou go</l>
               <l>It is great ſhame, a man to take exceſſe</l>
               <l>For co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly a beeſt wyll not do ſo</l>
               <l>Fle from ſlouth, it is a pleaſaunt foo</l>
               <l>A dilygent man wynneth, for body and ſoule</l>
               <l>Where as a ſlouthfull man, may chaunce loſe all</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Fle the fylthy ſynne of lecherye</l>
               <l>For it is that, that god doth greatly hate</l>
               <l>Beware thou ſpeke, no wordes of rybaudrye</l>
               <l>For all that here, therof ſome harme ſhall take</l>
               <l>For auery worde,<note place="margin">
                     <q>Ex abunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis cordis os loqit<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abur"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>ur</ex>
                        </expan>. <bibl>Mathewe. 12.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note> acounte thou muſt nede make</l>
               <l>Thy tonge wyll ſhewe, playnly what thou arte</l>
               <l>A fylthy tonge, declareth a fylthy herte</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Laboure truely, for to ſuſteyne thy nede</l>
               <l>To kepe thy body, from all indygence</l>
               <l>Couet the blyſſe of heuyn,<note place="margin">
                     <q>Habebis The<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſauros in celo. <bibl>Mathewe. 19. Marke. 12.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note> for thy mete</l>
               <l>Couet contrycyon, for all thyne offence</l>
               <l>Couet clene herte, and clene conſcyence</l>
               <l>Couet heuenly rycheſſe, that laſteth aye</l>
               <l>whiche no thefe can ſtele, nor bere away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ The .x. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes,<note place="margin">
                     <q>In via teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tuoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de lectatus ſum ſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cut in oi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bus di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uitijs. <bibl>Pſ. 118</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note> loke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou kepe &amp; holde</l>
               <l>with all thy power, vnto thy lyues ende</l>
               <l>Delyte in them, more then in ſyluer or golde</l>
               <l>Loue all creatures, be it foo or frende</l>
               <l>None is ſo euyl,<note place="margin">
                     <q>Maledicti qui declinant a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dat<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> tuis. <bibl>Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note> but that he may amende</l>
               <l>And mekely loke, vpon thy ſelfe with all</l>
               <l>None is ſo iuſt, but that he may fall</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:22464:3"/>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>It is a vertue,<note place="margin">
                     <q>
                        <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 chunk">
                           <desc>…</desc>
                        </gap>em pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>tur ꝓpter iuſtitiam. <bibl>Mathewe. 5.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note> that is ryght excellent</l>
               <l>Though thou ſomtyme, for trouth do ſuffre wronge</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalte neuer be ſhamed, though thou be ſhent</l>
               <l>To pleaſe god,<note place="margin">
                     <q>Penitemini er<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>go et conuerte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mini, vt delean<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tur <choice>
                           <abbr>pcta</abbr>
                           <expan>peccata</expan>
                        </choice> 
                        <choice>
                           <abbr>vra</abbr>
                           <expan>vostra</expan>
                        </choice>. <bibl>Actes. 3.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note> ſet all thy hole entent</l>
               <l>Fle great othes and lyes, for they be euyll</l>
               <l>For all lyers, be the chyldren of the deuyll</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Haue ſtedfaſt fayth,<note place="margin">
                     <q>Quicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducauerit pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, et biberit calicem dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne / reꝰ erit. corporis et ſan guinis dn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>i. <bibl>1. Corynthi. 8</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note> with parfyte reuerence</l>
               <l>Vnto the holy ſacramentes all</l>
               <l>The ſpecyall remedy, for thyne offence</l>
               <l>To ryſe agayne by, whan that thou doeſt fall</l>
               <l>Ordeyned of god, therfore mooſt ſpecyall</l>
               <l>Very contrycyon, with confeſſyon true</l>
               <l>To ſcape the payne,<note place="margin">
                     <q>Confiteamur peccata noſtra quonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fidelis eſt deus vt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittat nobis. <bibl>1. Iohan. 1.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note> that for the ſynne is dewe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ But where the ſerpent, lurketh in theyr herte</l>
               <l>They ſaye that confeſſyon, is ryght nought</l>
               <l>He is ſo lothe, from them to departe</l>
               <l>They ſaye it is yuough,<note place="margin">
                     <q>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fitemini al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter utrum p<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata veſtra. <bibl>Iames. 5.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note> god knoweth our thought</l>
               <l>we ſhall befafe, Chriſt hath ſo dere vs bought</l>
               <l>But who ſo dothe, confeſſyon diſpyſe</l>
               <l>The ſacrament of the aultre,<note place="margin">
                     <q>Quodcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueritis ſuꝑ ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ram, erunt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luta et in ceis. <bibl>Mathewe. 16.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note> ſetteth at lytell pryſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>¶ Faſtynge and prayer, my chylde ſe that thou vſe</l>
               <l>To exclude ſynne, with all thy hole entent</l>
               <l>Holy brede,<note place="margin">
                     <q>Hoc autem ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nꝰ demonioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eiicitur, niſi per orationem et ieiunium. <bibl>Mathewe. 17 Mathe. 9.</bibl>
                     </q>
                  </note> and holy water, do thou not refuſe</l>
               <l>In takyng of them, be thou ryght reuerent</l>
               <l>Thynke they were ordeyned, for a good entent</l>
               <l>A ſpecyall vertue, ſhalt thou fynde therin</l>
               <l>Agaynſt wycked ſpyrytes, and venyall ſynne.</l>
            </lg>
            <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
               <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:22464:3"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
